Guide to the Betsy Gamble Hansen papers, 1902-2003 and undated RL.10055
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Betsy Gamble Hansen papers
1902-2003 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hansen, Betsy Gamble.
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
RL.10055
5.5 Linear Feet 11 boxes
Betsy Gamble Hansen was an author and Duke University alumna. In 2000, she founded the Oglethorpe University Women's Network, and she belonged to Duke University's Council on Women's Studies for three years. The Betsy Gamble Hansen Papers include drafts of and papers related to Gamble's writings, especially related to her book, Portals, Menzies family correspondence, clippings, and other papers. Materials range in date from 1902 to 2003, with the bulk being from 1902-1960 and 1996-2003.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical note
Betsy Gamble Hansen was an author and Duke University alumna. While at Duke, she majored in English and was a member of Pi Beta Phi sorority. After graduating, she wrote for the "Women's Pages" section of the High Point Enterprise, contributed to the Beaufort, NC Gazette in 1951 and was a small business owner in Charlotte, NC for many years. Hansen also wrote and directed puppet plays in Durham, N.C. She became active in UNICEF in 1989, eventually serving on UNICEF's national board. In 2000, she founded the Oglethorpe University Women's Network, and she belonged to Duke University's Council on Women's Studies for three years. With her husband of 53 years, Harald Hansen, Betsy had two children, Edward Eugene Hansen and Brandon Hansen Frein.
Collection Overview
The Betsy Gamble Hansen papers are organized into two series. The Writings series includes drafts of Hansen's 2003 novel Portals, iterations of which existed under the titles A Communion of Saints, A Gathering of Saints and Sinners, The Hawk and the Myna Bird, and Tapestry Tales. Also included in this series are papers related to the publication of the book, including publishing contracts, typeface samples, prospectuses, copyright forms, and estimates. The Menzies Family correspondence and other papers series contains letters received by Hansen's grandmother, E.B. Menzies, of Hickory, North Carolina, and her immediate family, clippings, and other papers. The bulk of the correspondence in this series was written by Menzies's sons, Bruce, George, and Tom Menzies, and her daughters Mary Stuart Menzies Tarrant and Jane Menzies Gamble (Betsy Gamble Hansen's mother). Other frequent correspondents include Tom's wife, Frances Menzies, and George's wife, Betty Menzies. Also included are birthday cards, Christmas cards, and letters for E.B. Menzies from friends. Two folders labeled "Family Correspondence" consist of correspondence between E.B. Menzies's children and their spouses. Peppered throughout these folders are letters from E.B. Menzie's grandchildren, including Betsy Gamble Hansen.
Mrs. E. B. Menzies was born Reesie Tipton Warren in 1880 in Emory, Virignia and died in 1961. She lived most of her life in Hickory, NC. She married Edward Bruce Menzies in 1902, and they remained together until Edward died in 1924. Most of the pre-1930 correspondence in the collection consists of letters from E.B. Menzies's extended family and a few letters from her children while away at camp. The children wrote infrequently in the 1930s. During this time Tom, George, and Bruce traveled across the country from their hometown of Hickory, North Carolina, in search of work, while Jane and Mary Stuart remained at home. From 1932-1935, the three men each attended the Colorado School of Mines and performed construction work for the Works Progress Administration (WPA) project to build the Hoover Dam, then held temporary jobs in several different cities before settling in California. Tom and Bruce attended college while George appears to have continued working.
During World War II, each of E.B. Menzies's sons enlisted as United States Navy Seabees in the Pacific Theater, and began to write home much more frequently. Tom graduated in 1942 and was immediately subject to the draft, while Bruce and George began service several months later. None of the three men appear to have seen much conflict, and each survived the war unharmed, although Bruce did stay in a Navy Hospital for some time, apparently due to a stomach illness. Jane and Mary Stuart kept in frequent contact with their brothers throughout the war. All three men were discharged by 1945.
In the late 1940s and 1950s, each of E.B. Menzies's sons settled in California with their wives and children. George began working for a rail line, Tom took a job at a mill, and Bruce sold insurance. E.B. Menzies moved to California to teach for two years before moving back to North Carolina. Each of her children kept in regular correspondence with her throughout the 1950s, but the letters stop in 1961, when E.B. Menzies died.
In addition to the correspondence in this series, this series contains clippings and other papers compiled by E.B. Menzies, including a small amount of financial papers, prescriptions, and materials relating to her children.
Provenance
The Betsy Gamble Hansen papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in May 2013.
Arrangement
Materials in the Writings series are arranged alphabetically by folder title. Correspondence in the Menzies Family correspondence and other papers series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, then chronologically. Original folder titles have, for the most part, been retained.
Related Materials
Jean O'Barr Papers, 1974-2008 (Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library) Margaret Taylor Smith papers, 1918-2010 and undated, bulk 1980-2008 (Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Women's history -- United States; North Carolina -- Social life and customs; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States; Southern States -- Social conditions; United States. Navy. Appointments and Retirements; Hansen, Betsy Gamble.; Menzies Family.; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Writings, 1995-2003 and undated; 7 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The Writings series includes drafts of Hansen's 2003 novel, Portals, which also appears to have existed under the early titles A Communion of Saints, A Gathering of Saints and Sinners, The Hawk and the Myna Bird, and Tapestry Tales. Also included in this series are papers related to the publication of Portals, including publishing contracts, typeface samples, prospectuses, copyright forms, and estimates.
  - Communion of Saints annotated, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Communion of Saints chapter drafts, 1995-2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Communion of Saints draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Communion of Saints early draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Communion of Saints: miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Communion of Saints proposal, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - A Gathering of Saints and Sinners chapter drafts: chapters 1-3, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - A Gathering of Saints and Sinners chapter drafts: chapters 4-12, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A Gathering of Saints and Sinners chapter drafts: chapters 13-25, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - A Gathering of Saints and Sinners draft (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Hawk and the Myna Bird, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Index cards - episodes, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Notes, 1995 and undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Portals - the author's annotated copy, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapters 1-2, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapters 3-4, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapter 5, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapters 6-7, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapters 8-9, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapters 10-12, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapters 13-15, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapter 16, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapters 17-18, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapters 19-21, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Portals chapter drafts: chapters 22-23, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Portals contractor: Wings, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Portals copyright form, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Portals cover/order forms, 2003 and undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Portals early edits of third draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Portals estimate on hard copy, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Portals etsc types, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Portals final proof, annotated, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Portals first drafts, writings not used, notes from Barbara (1 of 2), undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Portals first drafts, writings not used, notes from Barbara (2 of 2), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Portals first and second draft prospectus, 1997-1999 and undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Portals handwritten notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Portals miscellaneous drafts (1 of 3), undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Portals miscellaneous drafts (2 of 3), undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Portals miscellaneous drafts (3 of 3), undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Portals miscellaneous research, notes and drafts, 1995-1997 and undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Portals overview, 1995-2003 and undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Portals third draft: forward and chapters 1-6, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Tapestry Tales chapters 1-6, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Tapestry Tales first draft (1 of 2), 1995-1996 and undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Tapestry Tales first draft (2 of 2), 1995-1996 and undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Tapestry Tales miscellaneous, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Tapestry Tales overview, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Menzies Family correspondence and other papers, 1902-1961 and undated; 4 boxes
  The Menzies Family correspondence and other papers series contains letters received by Hansen's grandmother, E.B. Menzies, and her immediate family, clippings, and other papers. The bulk of the correspondence in this series was written by Menzies's sons, Bruce, George, and Tom Menzies, and her daughters Mary Stuart Menzies Tarrant and Jane Menzies Gamble (Betsy Gamble Hansen's mother). Other frequent correspondents include Tom's wife, Frances Menzies, and George's wife, Betty Menzies. Also included are birthday cards, Christmas cards, and letters for E.B. Menzies from friends. Two folders labeled "Family Correspondence" consist of correspondence between E.B. Menzies's children and their spouses. Peppered throughout these folders are letters from E.B. Menzie's grandchildren, including Betsy Gamble Hansen. In addition to the correspondence in this series, also included are clippings and other papers compiled by E.B. Menzies, including a small number of financial papers, prescriptions, and materials relating to her children.
  - Letters from Jane Gamble to E.B. Menzies, circa 1920-1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Betty Menzies to E.B. Menzies, 1952-1960 and undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Bruce Menzies to E.B. Menzies (1 of 6), circa 1920-1942 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Bruce Menzies to E.B. Menzies (2 of 6), 1943 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Bruce Menzies to E.B. Menzies (3 of 6), 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Letters from Bruce Menzies to E.B. Menzies (4 of 6), 1948-1957 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Bruce Menzies to E.B. Menzies (5 of 6), 1958-1961 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Bruce Menzies to E.B. Menzies (6 of 6), undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Frances Menzies to E.B. Menzies, 1944-1957 and undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Letters from George Menzies to E.B. Menzies (1 of 3), circa 1930-1941 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Letters from George Menzies to E.B. Menzies (2 of 3), 1942-1945 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Letters from George Menzies to E.B. Menzies (3 of 3), 1948-1961 and undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Letters from Tom Menzies to E.B. Menzies (1 of 4), circa 1920-1941 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Tom Menzies to E.B. Menzies (2 of 4), 1942-1945 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Tom Menzies to E.B. Menzies (3 of 4), 1946-1954 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Tom Menzies to E.B. Menzies (4 of 4), 1955-1961 and undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Mary Stuart Tarrant to E.B. Menzies, 1944-1954 and undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Letters to E.B. Menzies from friends, 1902-1961 and undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Birthday cards for E.B. Menzies, 1960 and undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Christmas cards for E.B. Menzies, 1958-1960 and undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Family correspondence (1 of 2), 1902-1949 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Family correspondence (2 of 2), 1950-1960 and undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1946-1955 and undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Other papers, 1928, 1942-1962 and undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Includes Tom Menzies's baptism record, an invitation to Bruce Menzies's wedding, a passage written by Bruce Menzies entitled "In Memory of Dad," a Delta Kappa Gamma Nu chapter directory dated 1959-1960, a script of a play by Katherine Bridges entitled "Trial of the Birds," and various receipts, checks, and prescriptions of E.B. Menzies.